Finding Aid for the Bennet Harvive Branscomb Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
- "O.C. Carmichael, The Man and the Citizen." Speech for Unveiling Carmichael Portrait, n.d.
- General Hospital Proposal (incomplete draft), n.d.
- Speech for Vanderbilt American Assembly, n.d.
- Remarks at dedication of Divinity School building and introduction of Liston Pope.
- Remarks at the Dedication of the A.B. Learned Graduate Science Hall, Vanderbilt University, Nov. 10.
- "Chance Remarks." Hustler.
- Remarks at dinner for President Stuntz on his retirement, n.d.
- Remarks at Rotary dinner at Vanderbilt for Ambassadors from Latin American countries.
- "Vanderbilt University - October 1946." Paper requested by Professor Henry Swint.
- Toast to the memory of the Commodore.
  - Speeches: Nashville area - Box 5, Folder 40.
- Address before the Rotary Club, Oct. 7, 1946.
- Address before the Civitan Club, Oct. 15, 1946.
- "What the Colleges Contribute to the Economy of Nashville." Address to the Nashville Chamber of Commerce, revised Dec. 1953.
- "The essence of Communism..." Article for the Nashville Tennessean, Sept. 20, 1959.
- "The College and University Library." West End Methodist, July 27, 1960. Speech at the Centennial Club, April 13, 1961.
- Speech at Cornerstone Laying Ceremony, Veterans' Administration Hospital, Nashville, Tenn., June 22, 1961.
- "The Common Market." Rotary Club, Feb. 12, 1962.
- Keynote Address, National Security Seminar, War Memorial Auditorium, Nashville, March 12, 1962.
- Address before the Nashville Rotary Club, April 13, 1964.
- Speech for the National Bank, Dec. 1964.
- "Some Observations on International Conferences." Centennial Club
- Jan. 25, 1966.
- Address before the Methodist Women's Group, Dec. 6, 1965.
- Address before the Rotary Coub, Nashville, June 13, 1966.
- Address to the Legislature, April 26, 1967.
- U.N. Workshop, Nashville, Oct. 1967.
- Address at the B'nai B'rith Testimonial dinner, n.d.
- "Teaching as a Career," n.d.
- Address at Stahlman dinner, n.d.
- Address at meeting of Nashville Chamber of Commerce, n.d.
- Address before Rotary Club, n.d.
- Address to the Optimist Club, n.d.
- Address to the Chamber of Coinnerce, n.d.
  - Speeches: Commencement (outside institutions) - Box 5, Folder 41.
- David Lipscomb College, June 5, 1950.
- University of Chicago, Dec. 22, 1950.
- Western Kentucky State College, June 3, 1954.
- University of Mississippi, May 27, 1956.
- Brandéis University, June 6, 1958.
- "The Guardians of Wisdom." Northwestern, 1958.
- Rice Institute, June 3, 1960 (also given at Scarritt, 1961 and University of Tennessee, 1962).
- University of Tennessee, March 17, 1962.
- Brooke Hill School, Birmingham, May 31, 1968.
- Belmont College, May 28, 1971.
- "Dynamic Education," Peabody of Scarritt, n.d.
- "The Grounds of Our Hope," Randolph-Macon College for Women, n.d. Commencement address, n.d.
  - Speeches: Academic occasions (outside institutions) - Box 5, Folder 42.
- "The Next Ten Years in Education." Policies and Problems in Higher Education. Seminar, April 1948.
- Address at University of Chattanooga. Opening convocation, Sept. 28, 1948. Speech on "The Future of College Libraries." Cambridge, Mass., March 31, 1949. Speech at Scarritt, Nov. 9, 1949.
- Address at inaugeration of President West, Meharry, Oct. 20, 1952.
- Peabody Sunday Vesper Series, June 10, 1956.
- Honors Day, George State College, May 7, 1958.
- "A Two-Way Street should have deliveries at both ends." Paper presented at annual meeting of the National Association of State Universities
- May 4, 1959.
- Speech at Emory University, Nov. 10, 1960.
- "The Colleges and the Business Community." Address at Birmingham-Southern College, Dec. 2, 1960.
- Address at Chattanooga University, n.d.
- Address at Birmingham-Southern, n.d.
- Phi Beta Kappa address at Emory University, n.d.
- Remarks at installation of Dr. Rhodes at Southwestern, n.d.
- Address at Fisk University on establishment of Phi Beta Kappa.
  - Speeches and Papers: Non-academic occasions (outside Nashville) - Box 6, Folder 43.
- Editorial, Oxonian, April 1943.
- "Cecil Rhodes," Rio de Janeiro, 1945.
- "Spiritual Values in Higher Education." Southern Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools, Memphis, Tenn., Dec. 13, 1946.
- Address before the Tennessee Public School Teachers Association, Jan. 10, 1947.
- "Mature Higher Education." Rotary Club of Birmingham, Alabama, Sept. 17, 1947.
- Address before the Tennessee Society of St. Louis, Jan. 10, 1948.
- Discussion on Medical Education, A.M.A., Feb. 9, 1948.
- Transcript of Proceedings, National Health Assembly, May 24, 1948.
- Speech made to National Association of Foreign Students Advisers, Cleveland
- Ohio, March 29, 1949.
- "The Responsibility of the Individual in the Present Crisis." Birmingham
- Alabama, Feb. 14, 1951.
- Address at the celebration of the One Hundred and Fiftieth anniversary of the founding of Huntsville, Alabama, Sept. 11, 1955.
- American Council Annual Meeting, Oct. 6, 1955.
- "The Changing Temper." Iron and Steel Institute, Birmingham, Alabama
- Oct. 23, 1967.
- Critique of Niebuhr's proposal for the Sealantic Fund, Nov. 16, 1959.
- "The Expansion of Higher Education." International Association of Universities, Mexico City, Sept. 8, 1960.
- Speech honoring Bill Elliott at luncheon on his retirement from Harvard University, ca. 1960.
  - Speeches, Papers, and Book Reviews: Religious issues - Box 6, Folder 44.
- "The Dramatic Instinct of Early Christianity." Presidential address delivered at the 31st annual meeting of the National Association of Biblical
- Instructors at Union Theological Seminary, N.Y.C., Dec. 27 and 28, 1940.
- "Jesus and Judaism." Lecture at the University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, 1942.
- "Jesus and Judaism." Lecture at Hebrew Union College, Cincinnati, Nov. 1942.
- "Paul's Attitude to the Law." Cincinnati, 1942.
- "The Church of the Second Century." Cincinnati, 1942.
- World Conference on Faith and Order, the American Theological Committee.
- The Report of the Committee. Christendom, vol. IX, no. 2, Spring 1944.
- Memorial to Frederic Moir Hanes North Carolina Medical Journal, vol. 8, no. 3, March 1947.
- "The Meaning of the New Testament." The Church of the Air Program, C.B.S., Nov. 16, 1947.
- "Some Mistakes which Parents Make." Cole Lecture Week, West End Church, April 16, 1950.
- "Seeking Faith." Series of talks on Faith in Action, N.B.C., Oct. 26, 1952.
- "Our Responsibility as Christians toward World Issues." Address to the women of St. George's Episcopal Church, Nashville, Feb. 20, 1962.
- Book Reviews:
- Die Jesusfrage im Neuzeitlichen Judentum Ein Beitrag gur Geschichte der Leben-Jesu-Forschung by Gosta Lindeskog. 1938.
- The Book of Revelation by E.F. Scott.
- The Search for the Real Jesus: A Century of Historical Study by C.C. McCown.
- Understanding the Parables of Our Lord, by Albert E. Barnett.
- The Nature and Purpose of the Gospels, by R.V.G. Tasker.
  - Clippings: Vanderbilt University, 1946-1963 - Box 6, Folder 45.
- "New Chancellor," Nashville Tennessean, Aug. 3, 1946.
- Holder, Bill. "Portrait of a Chancellor." Reprinted from the Nashville Tennessean Magazine, Sept. 29, 1946.
- Russell, Fred, "The Chancellor Visits Practice." Oct. 10, 1946.
- "Chancellor Branscomb-Man for the Job." Nashville Banner. (1946).
- "Chancellor Cites Vanderbilt's Important Role in the South." Nashville Banner. Aug. 3 (1946).
- Installation Proceedings at the Inauguration of Harvie Branscomb as Fourth Chancellor of Vanderbilt University, Feb. 4, 1947.
- Program of Inauguration of Bennett Harvie Branscomb as Fourth Chancellor of Vanderbilt University, Feb. 4, 1947.
- Remarks of Frank C. Rand, President Board of Trust at the Inauguration of Bennett Harvie Branscomb as Chancellor of Vanderbilt University, Feb. 4, 1947.
- "VU to Inaugurate Branscomb Feb. 4." (1946).
- "VU Chancellor to be Installed." (1946).
- Program for The Newcomen Society in North America at Nashville on March 16th, 1950. Branscomb, Harvie. "Be Yourselves1." Listen, 1954.
- Branscomb, Harvie. "Juror Finds His Duty 'Refreshing.1" July 2, 1957.
- Graves, John Temple. "Praised With a Loud Damn." Farmville, VA. Herald. Dec. 13, 1960.
- Christie, Amos. "Some Notes About Vanderbilt in the Old Days."
- Vanderbilt Alumnus. July/August 1969.
- Wilson, Owen H. "Early History of Medical Education in Nashville." Reprinted from Journal of the Tennessee Medical Association, Vol. 62, no. 9, Sept. 1969, pp. 819-829.
- "Reverence and Gratitude," n.d.
- "Nashvillians Attend Party in New York," n.d.
  - Clippings: Personal (Post-retirement) - Box 6, Folder 46.
- Barker, George. "He Put the Cap on 'Dynamite ! ' " Nashville Tennessean Magazine, Jan. 8, 1961.
- "Branscomb Testimonial Issue." Vanderbilt Hustler. Jan. 11, 1963.
- Branscomb, Harvie. "V.U. Alumni in Taiwan, Prosperity in Hong Kong." (Nashville Banner, 1964).
- Branscomb, Harvie. "Incisive Analysis of Communist Technique." (Nashville Banner, 1964).
- Branscanb, Harvie. "The Vastness of India, Complexity of Aid Plans." (Nashville Banner, 1964).
- Branscomb, Harvie. "Egypt: Mixture of Grandeur, Problems." (Nashville Banner, 1964).
- Branscomb, Harvie. "Hard Working Japan Is Dependable U.S. Ally." (Nashville Banner, 1964).
- Branscomb, Harvie. "V.U. Alumni in Taiwan, Prosperity in Hong Kong." (Nashville Banner, 1964).
- Dodson, Anne. "Multi-Nation Pact Reached By Diplomacy." Corpus Christi Caller. Dec. 14, 1965.
- "World Bank Officer Praises Dr. Branscomb." Nashville Banner, Feb. 14, 1967. Branscomb, Harvie. "Teaching with Books." June, 1973.
- "Branscomb." Vanderbilt Hustler. Oct. 27, 1978.
- Fine, Benjamin. "Free Interchange of Culture Urged."
  - Printed materials - Box 6.
- The American Oxonian. "Oliver Cromwell Carmichael (1891-1966)," pp. 48-50.
- The Baptist Student. "UNESCO, World Market for Ideas," pp. 6-9.
- The Competent College Student. An Essay on the Objectives and Quality of Higher Education. Discussion paper sponsored by the Tennessee Higher Education Commission and funded by a grant from the Ford Foundation, April 1977.
- "The Contribution of Moral and Spiritual Ideas to the Making of the American Way of Life." Lecture delivered at the University of Wisconsin, March 19, 1952.
- The Duke Divinity School Bulletin. Vol. 3, #3, Nov. 1942. "The Dramatic Instinct of Early Christianity," pp. 1-11.
- Gold Medallion, Distinguished Service Awards, Birmingham-Southern College.
- Governance of Public Higher Education in California. A Report prepared by the Academy for Educational Development, Inc., Oct. 8, 1968.
- Harvard Library Bulletin. Vol, 3, # 3, Autumn 1949. "The Future of Libraries in Academic Institutions," pp. 327-346.
- Higher Education in a Changing World. "Universities and World Affairs," pp. 69-79. (Addresses selected from the 1965 Conferences for the Visiting Fulbright-Hays Scholars in the United States).
- Learning Today. "Beyond Innovation, Forty Years of Teaching with Books" by David J. Martz, Jr. (A New Look at Harvie Branscomb's Teaching with Books).
- Library-College Journal. "Curing the Campus Coronary," pp. 13-16.
- National Association of State Universities in the United States of America. "A Two-Way Street Should Have Delivery at Both Ends," pp. 35-42.
- The Responsibility of Higher Education for Helping to Develop International Understanding. "Introductory Statement," pp. 3-4. (A Series of Papers Presented at the Annual Meeting of the American Council on Education, Oct. 6, 1955).
- "Spiritual Values in Higher Education." An address delivered before the 51st Annual Meeting of the Southern Association of Colleges and Secondary Schools, Memphis, Tennessee, Dec. 13, 1946.
- The State of the University. A Report from the Chancellor to Alumni and Friends of Vanderbilt University, Sept. 1, 1947.
- UNESCO in a Decisive Decade. "UNESCO and Education," pp. 4-9.
- Vanderbilt University - 'The Commodore's Best Investment 1.
- SUPPLEMENT
  - CORRESPONDENCE: (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Aug. 27 to Dr. H. M. Lydenberg., 1945 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Apr. 15 to Harold S. Vanderbilt., 1947 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - May 26 to Harold S. Vanderbilt., 1950 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - June 11 to Helen Ann Stavely; Oct. 21 to Winifred R. Long., 1959 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Mar. 22 to Col. G. M. Dorland., 1962 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Feb. 19 to Robert N. Buchanan, Jr.; Apr. 29 to Harold S. Vanderbilt Nov. 27 to Devereux Lake., 1963 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Jan. 2 to Mrs. Neil Cargil; Mar. 18 to Harold S. Vanderbilt; May 16 to Dr. Franz von Hildebrand; Dec. 26 to The Honorable J. L. Huang., 1964 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Jan. 7, June 3, June 11 to Harold S. Vanderbilt; Aug. 3 to Vice-President Hubert Humphrey; Aug. 6 to Richard A. Humphrey; Oct. 13 to Betty Hamilton (Mrs. John Andrew)., 1965 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - July 5 to Dr. Alberto Gianza Paz; July 6 to William J. Gill; July 9 to Eugene R. Black; July 26 to Dr. Ricardo Dstiaz Hochleitner; Nov. 16 to John J. Hertz; Dec. 14 to Harold [S. Vanderbilt]., 1966 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Jan. 5 to Dean John Harvey; May 5 to Mrs. Harold Huggins; May 25 to Frank Godchaux, III; Sept. 15 to John S. and R. D. Herbert, Jr., 1967 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Jan. 8 to Rob Roy [Purdy]., 1968 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - June 25 to Vanderbilt Board of Trust., 1969 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Nov. 23 to Winfield Dunn., 1970 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - June 10 to Chancellor Alexander Heard; Aug. 3 to Sam Fleming., 1971 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Mar. 24 to Jack; Nov. 13 to the Hon. John Eric Jonsson., 1972 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Jan. 4 to The Hon. John Eric Jonsson; May 7 to Dr. Rufus Harris., 1973 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - July 9 to Dr. R. Gordon Hoxie; Oct. 3 to Herbert C. Stockham., 1974 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - Aug. 2 to Ray Carlson., 1982 (Box 6, Folder 47)
    - To the Reverend Minor E. Powers; to Mrs. Harold S. Vanderbilt., Undated (Box 6, Folder 47)
- INCOMING CORRESPONDENCE: (Box 6, Folder 48)
  Bess, Fred H., (1); July 29, 1981.
  Betancur-Mejia, Gabriel, (1); Dec. 18, 1963.
  Blum, Jeffery W., (1); (1980).
  Buchanan, Robert N., Jr., (1); Feb. 4, 1963.
  Buek, Charles W., (1); Apr. 26, 1979 (to Alexander Heard).
  Califano, Joseph A., Jr., (1); Nov. 1, 1966.
  Cater, Douglass, (1); Feb. 2, 1966.
  Chandler, Robert K., (1); Mar. 26, 1962.
  Cleveland, Harlan, (2); Apr. 8, 1964, July 26, 1965.
  Coniglio, John, (1); Nov. 21, 1979.
  Cookey, S. J., (1); Dec. 6, 1965.
  Dorland, G. M., (1); Mar. 12, 1962.
  Ellington, Buford, (1); Oct. 13, 1967.
  Elliott, Don R., (1); Sept. 17, 1957.
  Forstman, Jack, (1); Sept. 29, 1980.
  Garner, Robert L., (2); Jan. 18, 1968, Dec. 10, 1969.
  Georgescu-Roegen, Nicholas, (1); Dec. 26, 1967.
  Gill, William J., (2); June 22, July 12, 1966.
  Halsema, James J., (1); Feb. 29, 1964.
  Hamilton, Betty, (1); Sept. 12, 1965.
  Harrar, J. G., (1); June 19, 1969.
  Harris, Robert J., (1); June 23, 1966.
  Harris, Rufus C., (1); June 6, 1973.
  Harrison, Tinsley R., (5); Sept. 9, 1968, Jan. 22, Nov. 19, Dec. 3, Dec. 19, 1973.
  Harwell, R. W., (1); Mar. 1, 1968.
  Haury, Karl E., (1); Sept. 20, 1968.
  Hays, Bill, (1); May 28, 1973.
  Heard, Alexander, (1); July 5, 1967 (memo to Professor Eugene Klatte).
  Heard, Alexander, (1); Aug. 31, 1981.
  Heard, Jean, (1); June 9, 1977.
  Hertz, John J., (1); Oct. 25, 1966.
  Hildebrand, Franz v., (1); June 3, 1964.
  Hill, S. Richardson, Jr., M.D., (1); Nov. 13, 1973.
  Hogarth, Charles P., (1); Nov. 17, 1972.
  Hope, Guy, (1); Sept. 28, 1966.
  Hornig, Donald F., (1); Nov. 29, 1965.
  Horrocks, Norman, (1); Dec. 1, 1970.
  Houston, Frank K., (5); Jan. 12, Jan. 30, Mar. 30, July 13, Sept. 9, 1970.
  Howard, William F., (1); Apr. 11, 1973.
  Hoxie, R. Gordon, (6); Feb. 28, Apr. 30, Nov. 13, 1970, Aug. 4, 1972, June 15, July 6, 1973.
  Huang, J. L., (1); June 11, 1974.
  Huggins, Juanita R. (Mrs. Howard), (1); Apr. 27, 1967.
  Humphrey, Hubert H., (1); July 28, 1965.
  Humphrey, Richard A., (2); July 23, July 26, 1965.
  Jacobson, Timothy, (1); Oct. 31, 1978.
  Kite, Liz and Adkisson, Bill, (1); Oct. 21, 1974 (memo).
  Lan, Lun Thuy, (1); May 18, 1961.
  Ligon, Wister H., (1); Feb. 12, 1962.
  Long, Winifred R., (1); Oct. 7, 1959.
  McCurdy, Charles P., Jr., (1); Oct. 20, 1959.
  Mubyarto, (1); May 19, 1961.
  Nelson, J. Robert, (1); Sept. 21, 1959.
  Ochsner, Alton, (1); (1967).
  Parr, Grant, (1); Dec. 7, 1950.
  Powers, Minor E., (2); Dec. 22, 1961, Feb. 7, 1962.
  Samuels, Essie, (2); Dec. 7, 1973.
  Stahlman, James G., (1); June 6, 1966.
  Stahlman, Mildred, (1); Apr. 25, 1973.
  Stevenson, Alec B., (1); Oct. 20, 1961.
  Swint, Henry Lee, (4); June 1, 1970, Jan. 12, Oct. 19, 1972, May 21, 1976.
  TeSelle, Sallie M., (1); June 1, 1976.
  Vanderbilt, Gertrude, (2); Nov. 10, Nov. 16, 1970.
  Vanderbilt, Harold S., (15); Mar. 25, July 13, 1964, Feb. 15, Mar. 5, Aug. 6, Nov. 15, 1965, July 7, Dec. 20, 1966, Apr. 24, Nov. 16, Nov. 20, Dec. 11, 1967, May 21, July 8, 1968, Feb. 9, 1970.
  Vanderbilt, William H., (1); Sept. 2, 1970.
  Vaughn, W. S., (2); Aug. 6, Aug. 12, 1970.
  Wade, John W. (1); May 4, 1955.
  Wallace, Louis D., (1); Feb. 14, 1962.
  Warren, A. Sam, (1); Apr. 18, 1972 (to Vanderbilt Alumnus).
  Weinreb, Joseph, M.D., (1); Sept. 15, 1948.
  West, Elmer S., (1); Feb. 26, 1971.
  Windham, A. B., Jr., (1); Feb. 12, 1962.
  Youmans, John B., (1); May 15, 1950.
  Young, Bert E., (1); July 26, 1946 (to Robert Lester).
  Unidentified (Herman), (1); Nov. 7, 1978.
  Speeches, papers, reports, programs, minutes of meetings, and newspaper clippings (Miscellaneous): (Box 6, Folder 49 and Box 7, Folder 50).